---
title: "RRR: Replicating Resampling with Rsampling"
author: "Paulo Inácio Prado, Alexandre Oliveira and André Chalom"
date: "April 2016"
output:
  rmarkdown::html_vignette:
    fig_width: 5
    fig_height: 5
    fig_caption: true
vignette: >
  %\VignetteIndexEntry{Introduction to Rsampling}
  %\VignetteEngine{knitr::rmarkdown}
  \usepackage[utf8]{inputenc}
---

```{r setup, echo = FALSE}
knitr::opts_chunk$set(
    collapse=TRUE,
    comment = NA,
    prompt = TRUE
    )
set.seed(42)
```

## Overview

This guide is an introduction to the **Rsampling** package, which replicates in R the functions
of the *Resampling Stats* add-in fro Excell.
(http://www.resample.com/).

These functions are used in a workflow that summarizes the logic
behind significance tests:

1. Define a statistic of interest;
2. Define the null hypothesis;
3. Get the statistic of interest distribution under null hypothesis;
4. If the probability of the observed statistic of interest ocurring under
null hypothesis is lower than a critical value, reject the null hypothesis.

*Resampling Stats* 's main idea is to facilitate the understanding of this logic,
by making the user execute each step in a spreadsheet, with the aid of
some macros.

**Rsampling** 's package aims at enabling this same training proccess
in R. Keeping the original workflow is favored over performance.


The sections following instalation instructions are examples of the
simpler and most common applications of **Rsampling**. You may refer
to the package help pages to learn about all other functionalities.


## Instalation
The package **Rsampling** is avaible on GitHub.
To install it, use the `install_github` function from package devtools:

```{r installation, eval=FALSE}
library(devtools)
install_github(repo = 'lageIBUSP/Rsampling')
```
Then load it with:

```{r load library}
library(Rsampling)
```

## Shuffling a column to test difference between groups

The `embauba` dataframe contains the data on presence and absence of lianas
on *Cecropia* trees of two morphotypes (white and red).


```{r inspecting object embauba}
head(embauba)
summary(embauba)
```
For more details on the data please refer to
help page (`?embauba`).

### Study hypothesis

The original study's hypothesis is that
ants that lives within the hollow trunks of *Cecropia* remove lianas from these trees. 
The prediction is that *Crecopia*  trees of the red morphotype would be less infested by lianas than
the white ones, because they shelter ant colonies more often.
In fact, this difference is observed in the proportions of trees
infested by lianas in the sample:

```{r proportion of infestation by morphotype}
tapply(embauba$with.vines, embauba$morphotype, mean)
```
### Null hypothesis

The null hypothesis is that the proportion of infested trees are equal at
the population from where the samples were drawn.
Under this hypothesis, a liana has the same chance of occurence in both morphotypes.
We can simulate this null hypothesis
by shuffling the presence of lianas between trees
in the data table.

### Statistic of interest

For each simulation we have to calculate our
**statistic of interest**, which is the
difference of infestation by lianas
between the two morphs.
We then create a function to calculate this statistic:

```{r statistic of interest cecropia}
emb.ei <- function(dataframe){
    props <- tapply(dataframe$with.vines, dataframe$morphotype, mean)
    props[[1]] - props[[2]]
}
## Verifying
emb.ei(embauba)
```
### Distribution of statistics under the null hypothesis

Then we run the simulation with the function
`Rsampling`:

```{r cecropia resampling, results="hide"}
emb.r <- Rsampling(type = "normal", dataframe = embauba,
                   statistics = emb.ei, cols = 2, ntrials = 1000)
```
**What does this command mean?**

* `type = "normal"` indicates a randomization of a whole dataset (the most basic type of randomization, afterwards you'll se other types).
* `dataframe = embauba` indicates the data table
* `statistics = emb.ei` indicates the function that calculates the statistic of
			interest from the data table.
* `cols = 2` indicates that the randomization must be done over the second column
		of the data table.
* `ntrials = 1000` indicates the number of simulation repetitions.


The distribution of the statistic of interest at the simulation
didn't even include the observed value:

```{r cecropia null distribution, fig.cap="Distribution of the differences between the proportions of red and white *Cecropia* trees with lianas obtained from 1000 simulations of the null hypothesis. The null hypothesis is that the proportion of infested trees are equal at the population from where the samples were drawn. The red line marks the difference observed in the samples and the gray area is the *acceptance region* of the null hypothesis."}
dplot(emb.r, svalue = emb.ei(embauba), pside="Greater",
      main = "Frequency distribution of the statistic of interest",
      xlab = "Statistic of interest")
```

### Decision: should we reject the null hypothesis?

As usual in the  biological sciences,
we adopt the criteria of rejecting
the null hypothesis if the probability of
the statistic of interest under the null hypothesis
is under 5% (p < 0.05).

The area not highlighted in grey marks the the top 5%
of the statistic distribution under the null hypothesis.
Thus, if the observed statistic is in the gray area we do not reject
the null hypothesis. This is called the *acceptance region* of H0.
As the observed value (red line) is outside the acceptance region,
H0 can be rejected.
You can also check this with a logical test in
R:

```{r cecropia test} 
sum(emb.r >= emb.ei(embauba))/1000 < 0.05
```

**Conclusion:** we reject the null hypothesis (p < 0.05).

## Shuffling within rows to test differences within pairs

The dataframe `azteca` contains the number of  *Azteca* sp ants
recruited by aqueous extracts of old and young leaves of *Cecropia* trees.

```{r inspecting object azteca}
head(azteca)
summary(azteca)
```
Learn more about the data at its help page (`?azteca`).

### Study hypothesis

The study hypothesis is that
recruitment is more intense when a
young leaf is damaged.
This hypothesis predicts that an extract made from young leaves would
recruit more ants than an extract made of old leaves.
Indeed this was the outcoe of the experiment:

```{r pairplot azteca, fig.cap = "Number ants that were recruited by aqueous extracts of young and old leaves of *Cecropia* trees. The extratcs were dropped in paired leaves of *Cecropia* trees that had colonies of *Azteca* ants. The lines link leaves of same experimental pair."}
splot(azteca$extract.new, azteca$extract.old,
           groups.names=c("Young leaves","Old leaves"),
           ylab="Number of recruited ants",
           xlab="Extract type")
```

### Null hypothesis

The null hypothesis is that the recruitment caused by each extract
is the same. Note that the experiment was paired in order to control for the other sources of variation.
Thus, to simulate the null hypothesis we have to
shuffle the number of recruited ants **within** each pair of
leaves.

### Statistic of interest

For each simulation we calculate our
**statistic of interest**, which is the
mean of the difference of recruited ants within each pair of leaves.
We thus create a  function calculate the statistic of interest from the data table:

```{r statistics of interest azteca}
azt.ei <- function(dataframe){
    diferencas <- with(dataframe, extract.new - extract.old)
    mean(diferencas)
}
## Observed value
azt.ei(azteca)
```
In the experiment the young leaf extract recruited on average
`r round(azt.ei(azteca),1)` ants than the old leaf extract, for each pair.

### Distribution of the statistic under null hypothesis

As the pairs are at rows of our dataframe,
we simulate the null hypothesis shuffling values
within each row:

```{r azteca resampling, results="hide"}
azt.r <- Rsampling(type = "within_rows", dataframe = azteca,
                   statistics = azt.ei, cols = 2:3, ntrials = 1000)
```

We changed the argument `type = "within rows"` to indicate that
the values are now shuffled within the lines.
The argument `cols = 2:3` indicates the columns of the dataframe
which contain the counts to be shuffled.

A difference equal to or greater than that observed was very rare
in the distribution of the statistic of interest:

```{r azteca null distribution, fig.cap="Frequency distributions of the difference of the number of ants recruited by the two types of extracts in 1000 simulations of the null hypothesis. The null hypothesis is that both extracts recruit ants equally. The red line marks the difference observed in the samples and the gray area is the *acceptance region* of the null hypothesis."}
dplot(azt.r, svalue = azt.ei(azteca), pside="Greater",
      main = "Distribution of the statistic of interest under H0",
      xlab = "Statistic of interest")
```

### Decision: shoul we reject the null hypothesis?

Again, the distribution of the statistic of interest shows that the observed value of the statistc is outside the acceptance region for the null hypothesis under our significance criterion (5% chance of error).
The same result is found with the following logical test:

```{r azteca test} 
sum(azt.r >= azt.ei(azteca))/1000 < 0.05
```

**Conclusion:** we reject the null hypothesis (p<0.05).

#### Coda: one-sided and double-tailed tests.

So far we have tested the hypothesis that a value **equal to or higher** than the observed
can be generated by the null hypothesis. We call this an **one-tailed** or **one-sided** test, as
it would also be if our aim was testing if an equal or smaller value could be generated under null hypothesis.
In one-sided tests, the acceptance region comprises the null distribution except its 5% more extreme values.

But we might investigaet differences among grups without specifying its direction. For example,
prior knowledge could suggest the hypothesis that extracts of young and old leaves should recruit
different numbers of ants, but without any expectation concerning which extract would recruit more. This is a case
for a **two-tailed**  or **tow-sided** test. In a two-tailed test
the acceptance region is the center of the null distribution, except their
2.5% most extreme values at each side:

```{r azteca two-tailed null, fig.cap="Frequency distributions of the difference of the number of ants recruited by the two types of extracts in 1000 simulations of the null hypothesis. The null hypothesis is that both extracts recruit ants equally. The red line marks the difference observed in the samples and the gray area is the *acceptance region* of the null hypothesis for a two-tailed test"}
dplot(azt.r, svalue = azt.ei(azteca), pside="Two sided",
      main = "Two-tailed test",
      xlab = "Statistics of interest")
```

## Randomization with replacement

The data frame `peucetia` contains data from an experiment of substract choice
by spiders of the genus *Peucetia*.
Twenty-seven spiders were kept in Petri dishes
covered with two substrates (sheets with and without gladulosos trichomes).
In six inspections for every plate it was registered
if each spider was on the leaves with trichomes.

```{r inspecionando objeto peucetia}
head(peucetia)
```
Learn more about the data at its help page (`?peucetia`).

### Study hypothesis

The study hypothesis is that
spiders prefer to hunt in plants
with glandulous hair, where catching prey
is easier.
The forecast for the experiment is
that spiders should be most
of the time on leaves with thricomes.
In fact, most spiders were on the leaves with
trichomes for 4 or more inspections:

```{r barplot peucetia, fig.cap = "Número de inspeções em que as 27 aranhas foram registradas em folhas com tricomas, em um experimento de preferência por substratos."}
## Número de inspeções em que estava em folha com tricomas
n.insp <- apply(peucetia, 1, sum)
barplot(table(factor(n.insp, levels=0:6)),
        xlab="N de inspeções em que estava na folha com tricoma",
        ylab="N de aranhas")

```

### Null hypothesis

The null hypothesis is that there is no preference.
One half of the plates were covered with each
leaf type, the null expectation
is that the spiders would be
in the area covered by leaves with trichomes in half of the inspections,
on average.
This expectation has the premise that each inspection
is an indepedent event. 

### Statistics of interest

For each simulation we have to calculate our
**statistic of interest**, which is the 
average number of inspections where the spiders were on leaves with trichomes.
A function for this:

```{r estatistica de interesse peucetia}
peu.ei <- function(dataframe){
    mean(apply(dataframe, 1, sum))
}
## Observed value
peu.ei(peucetia)
```

The spiders were registered on overage `r round(peu.ei(peucetia),2)`
of the 6 inspections on the area covered with leaves with thricomes.

### Distribution of the statistic under the null hypothesis

To simulate our null hypothesis, we created a
*data frame* with the same structure, wherein each
spider is on leaves with thricomes on half of the inspections.

```{r peucetia H0}
peu.H0 <- matrix( rep(c(TRUE,FALSE), each = 3),
                 nrow = nrow(peucetia), ncol = ncol(peucetia), byrow=TRUE)
## Converts in data.frame
peu.H0 <- data.frame(peu.H0)
## veryifing
head(peu.H0)
```
Then we simulate the null hypothesis by sampling each line
with reposition [^3]:

```{r peucetia resampling, results="hide"}
peu.r <- Rsampling(type = "within_rows", dataframe = peu.H0,
                   statistics = peu.ei, ntrials = 1000, replace=TRUE)
```

The argument `replace = TRUE` indicates sampling with replacement.
In this case, this amounts to draw an independent position
for each spider at each inspection. The probability of the spider being at
the leaf with trichomes is 0.5 per drawing.

An average equal to or greater than that observed 
didn't ocurr at the simulated distribution of our statistic of interest:

```{r peucetia distribuicao nula, fig.cap="Distribuição do número médio de inspeções em que as aranhas estavam em folhas com tricomas, em 1000 simulações da hipótese nula de ausência de preferência por substrato. A linha vermelha indica a média observada. A região de aceitação da hipótese nula para 5% de significância está delimitada em cinza."}
dplot(peu.r, svalue = peu.ei(peucetia), pside="Greater",
      main = "Distribuição da estatística de interesse sob H0",
      xlab = "Estatística de interesse")
```

### Decision: do we reject the null hypothesis?

Again we have a one-tailed test, and the observed value of the statistic of interest is not
within the null hypothesis region of acceptance (5%).
We confirm with the logical test of our significance criterion:
```{r peucetia teste} 
sum(peu.r >= peu.ei(peucetia))/1000 < 0.05
```

**Conclusion:** we reject the null hypothesis (p < 0,05).

## A more realistic null hypothesis?

In the previous example we simulate the hypothesis
null drawing a position for each spider for every
inspection. The premise is that the spider position
in an inspection does not affect its position in the other,
ie that inspections are
independent events.

But what if there is a temporal correlation for the position of spiders?
This can happen with spiders moving at a 
smaller frequency than the interval between
inspections. If this is true, subsequent records for a
leaf type may indicate only a trend for the spider staying in
place, and no preference. In this case the null hypothesis
should keep the number of inspections for each leaf type, altering
only the types.

### Null hypothesis

The proportion of inspections that spiders
remain in one of the substrates does not depend on
the substrate type (leaves with or without trichomes).

Therefore the null hypothesis is about the independence between the number
of inspections and type of substrate. We simulate this scenario
by scrambling the number of occasions between substrates,
for each spider. For this we will create a *data frame*
with number of inspections for each substrate:

```{r peucetia n de inspeções}
## N de inspeções em folha com tricoma
tric <- apply(peucetia, 1, sum)
## N de inspeções em folha lisa
lisa <- apply(peucetia, 1, function(x) sum(x==0))
## Monta o data frame
peu.H0b <- data.frame(tric=tric, lisa = lisa)
## Primeiras linhas
head(peu.H0b)
```


### Statistic of interest

The same statistic of interest can be applied for
different null hypotheses. So we keep the same from
our previous example: average number of inspections where
spiders were registered on leaves with trichomes.

But since the *data frame* to be randomized
has changed, we create a new function in R to
calculate the statistic of interest

```{r peucetia statistics 2}
peu.ei2 <- function(dataframe) mean(dataframe$tric)
## Verificando
peu.ei2(peu.H0b)
```


### Distribution of the statistic of interest under the null hypothesis

We simulate the null hypothesis scrambling the lines
of the *data frame* with the number of inspections for substrate:

```{r peucetia resampling 2, results="hide"}
peu.r2 <- Rsampling(type = "within_rows", dataframe = peu.H0b,
                   statistics = peu.ei2, ntrials = 1000)
```

The null distribution changed significantly when compared to the previous section.
But an average equal to or greater than the observed remained very rare:

```{r peucetia distribuicao nula 2, fig.cap="Distribuição do número médio de inspeções em que as aranhas estavam em folhas com tricomas, em 1000 simulações da hipótese nula de ausência de preferência por substrato, considerando tendência das aranhas permanecerem onde estão. A linha vermelha indica a média observada."}
dplot(peu.r2, svalue = peu.ei2(peu.H0b), pside="Greater",
      main = "Distribuição da estatística de interesse sob H0",
      xlab = "Estatística de interesse")
```

### Decision: do we reject the null hypothesis?

The observed value of the statistic of interest is not within our acceptance region.
Applying our significance criterion:

```{r peucetia teste 2} 
sum(peu.r2 >= peu.ei(peucetia))/1000 < 0.05
```

**Conclusion:** we reject the null hypothesis (p < 0,05).


## Structural zeros

In some datasets there are some observations with zero frequency
that are considered impossible to occur or be observed. For example,
the *dataframe* `pielou` has a number of ten occurances of
aphid species in twelve species of plants of the genus *Solidago*.

```{r pielou inspecionando objeto}
pielou
```

To learn more about this dataset refer to the help page (`?pielou`).
There are several instances with zero frequency.
We'll simulate a null hypothesis assuming
these frequencies are structural, that is, indicating
insect-plant associations that can not occur.

### Study Hypothesis

Our research hypothesis is that there is or there was sharing of resources among aphid
species. In this case, the observed associations should have resulted in decreased
insect niche overlap.

### Null hypothesis

Our null hypothesis is that the niche overlap does not differ from the expected
if instances of aphids on plants are independent.

### Statistics of interest

These data were used to illustrate an amplitude and overlap calculation of
niches. The expression proposed by the author
for the average niche overlap is the difference between
the Brillouin index of all values ​​and the sum of table columns.
The Brillouin index is a diversity measure in a collection of values ​​$ x_i $:

$$H = \frac{1}{N} \log N! \ - \ \frac{1}{N} \sum \log x_i !$$

Where $N = \sum x_i$. We're creating a function to make this calculation

```{r pielou indice de brillouin}
brillouin <- function(x, base=10) {
    N <- sum(x)
    lfactorial(N)/(log(base)*N)  -  sum(lfactorial(x)/log(base))/N
}
```

Then we create a function to calculate our statistic of interest

```{r pielou estatistica brillouin}
pielou.ei <- function(dataframe)
    brillouin( dataframe ) - brillouin( apply(dataframe,2,sum) )
```
Which value is:

```{r pielou estatistica de interesse}
pielou.ei(pielou)
```

### Distribution of the statistic of interest under the null hypothesis

To simulate our null hypothesis, we scramble the recorded incident numbers
of each species of aphids among the plants. Thus we create a situation where
hierachies of the preference of each species of aphid are maintained, but become independent.
Furthermore, we use the fix.zeroes' = TRUE` option to indicate that zero values are not
to be scrambled.

```{r , results="hide"}
pielou.r1 <- Rsampling(type = "within_rows", dataframe = pielou,
                   statistics = pielou.ei, ntrials = 1000, fix.zeroes = TRUE)
```

The observed value is greater than most values in the null distribution. As our
hypothesis is one-tailed (overlapping observed lower than expected by chance)
the observed value is in the null region of acceptance.

```{r pielou nula 2, fig.cap="Distribuição da sobreposição média de uso de plantas hospedeiras por espécies de pulgões, em 1000 simulações da hipótese nula de independência das espécies de inseto pelas plantas. As plantas sem ocorrência observadas dos pulgões foram consideradas não disponíveis (zeros estruturais). A linha vermelha indica a média observada."}
dplot(pielou.r1, svalue = pielou.ei(pielou), pside="Lesser",
      main = "Distribuição da estatística de interesse sob H0",
      xlab = "Estatística de interesse", xlim=c(0.3,0.6))
```

### Decision: do we reject the null hypothesis?

The observed value of our statistic of interrest is within the acceptance region.
Applying our significance criterion:

```{r  teste 2} 
sum(pielou.r1 <= pielou.ei(pielou))/1000 < 0.05
```

**Conclusion:** we do not reject the null hypothesis. (p > 0,05).


[^2]: Statistics.com LCC. 2009. Resampling Stats Add-in for Excel User’s Guide.
http://www.resample.com/content/software/excel/userguide/RSXLHelp.pdf

[^3]: There are more optized ways of doing this, but this one replicates
the drawing logic of an urn in *Rsampling Stats*
